<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-30T21:06:19+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Xinran’s Homepage</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><author><name>Xinran ZHAO</name><email>ee.xrzhao@my.cityu.edu.hk</email></author><entry><title type="html">Random Access: Sensing-Free or Sensing-Based?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research%20works/sensing-free-based/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Random Access: Sensing-Free or Sensing-Based?" /><published>2024-11-30T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-11-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research%20works/sensing-free-based</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research%20works/sensing-free-based/"><![CDATA[<p>With the ever-growing demand for low-latency services in machine-to-machine (M2M) communications, the delay performance of random access networks has become a primary concern, which critically depends on the sensing capability of nodes. To understand the effect of sensing on the optimal delay performance, the challenge lies in unifying the delay analysis of sensing-free Aloha and sensing-based Carrier Sense Multiple Access (CSMA) with various design features such as backoff and connection-free or connection-based. In this paper, based on a unified analytical framework, the mean queueing delay of data packets with Aloha and CSMA is characterized and optimized, with which the upper-bound of sensing time for CSMA to outperform Aloha in terms of the minimum mean queueing delay is further obtained. The analysis is also applied to the Random Access-Based Small Data Transmission (RA-SDT) schemes in 5G networks to investigate when and how significant their delay performance can be improved by sensing, which sheds important insights into practical access protocol design.</p>

<h3 id="related-paper">Related Paper</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>X. Zhao</strong> and L. Dai, “To Sense or Not To Sense: A Delay Perspective,” to appear in <em>IEEE Transactions on Communications</em>. <a href="(https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10750858)">Paper</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Xinran ZHAO</name><email>ee.xrzhao@my.cityu.edu.hk</email></author><category term="Research works" /><category term="Random Access" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With the ever-growing demand for low-latency services in machine-to-machine (M2M) communications, the delay performance of random access networks has become a primary concern, which critically depends on the sensing capability of nodes. To understand the effect of sensing on the optimal delay performance, the challenge lies in unifying the delay analysis of sensing-free Aloha and sensing-based Carrier Sense Multiple Access (CSMA) with various design features such as backoff and connection-free or connection-based. In this paper, based on a unified analytical framework, the mean queueing delay of data packets with Aloha and CSMA is characterized and optimized, with which the upper-bound of sensing time for CSMA to outperform Aloha in terms of the minimum mean queueing delay is further obtained. The analysis is also applied to the Random Access-Based Small Data Transmission (RA-SDT) schemes in 5G networks to investigate when and how significant their delay performance can be improved by sensing, which sheds important insights into practical access protocol design.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Random Access: Connection-Free or Connection-Based?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research%20works/connection-free-based/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Random Access: Connection-Free or Connection-Based?" /><published>2024-11-30T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-11-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research%20works/connection-free-based</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research%20works/connection-free-based/"><![CDATA[<p>According to whether a connection to the receiver is established before data transmission, random access schemes can be divided into two categories: connection-based and connection-free. For cellular networks, its connection-based access mechanism has been heavily criticized for being ill-suited to Machine-to-Machine (M2M) communications. With the existing studies overwhelmingly focusing on the physical-layer transmission and detection design of various connection-free access schemes, less attention has been paid to the fundamental understanding of when connection establishment could be beneficial.</p>

<p>The challenge originates from the lack of proper modeling of connection-based random access. In this paper, a scalable model that incorporates each node’s queueing behavior is proposed for connection-based slotted Aloha, based on which both the data throughput and the mean queueing delay of data packets are characterized, optimized, and compared with those for connection-free slotted Aloha. Conditions for beneficial connection establishment in terms of the optimal throughput and queueing delay performance are discussed and applied to cellular networks with the newly introduced Random Access-based Small Data Transmission (RA-SDT) schemes. The analysis offers important insights for the optimal access design of M2M communications.</p>

<h3 id="related-paper">Related Paper</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>X. Zhao</strong> and L. Dai, “Connection-Based Aloha: Modeling, Optimization, and Effects of Connection Establishment,” in <em>IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications</em>, vol. 23, no. 2, pp. 1008-1023, Feb. 2024. <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10154598">paper</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Xinran ZHAO</name><email>ee.xrzhao@my.cityu.edu.hk</email></author><category term="Research works" /><category term="Random Access" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[According to whether a connection to the receiver is established before data transmission, random access schemes can be divided into two categories: connection-based and connection-free. For cellular networks, its connection-based access mechanism has been heavily criticized for being ill-suited to Machine-to-Machine (M2M) communications. With the existing studies overwhelmingly focusing on the physical-layer transmission and detection design of various connection-free access schemes, less attention has been paid to the fundamental understanding of when connection establishment could be beneficial. The challenge originates from the lack of proper modeling of connection-based random access. In this paper, a scalable model that incorporates each node’s queueing behavior is proposed for connection-based slotted Aloha, based on which both the data throughput and the mean queueing delay of data packets are characterized, optimized, and compared with those for connection-free slotted Aloha. Conditions for beneficial connection establishment in terms of the optimal throughput and queueing delay performance are discussed and applied to cellular networks with the newly introduced Random Access-based Small Data Transmission (RA-SDT) schemes. The analysis offers important insights for the optimal access design of M2M communications.]]></summary></entry></feed>